Guide to the Sidney Altman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Sidney Altman papers
1967-2011
MS 1680
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
72
(90 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, publications files, laboratory notebooks, edited manuscripts, and research data, which document Sidney Altman's research in nucleic acid chemistry.
Altman, Sidney
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Received from Sidney Altman, 1995, 2012 and 2013.
Conditions Governing Access
Accession 2012-M-045 is open for research. The original accession of the Sidney Altman papers is unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access to the original accession should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks. Accession 2013-M-048 is closed to researchers until January 3, 2033, or the death of William H. McClain, Halvorson Professor, University of Wisconsin-Madison, whichever occurs first.
Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
Biographical / Historical
Sidney Altman was born on May 8, 1939, in Montreal, Quebec. He received a B.S. in physics from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1960 and a Ph.D. in biophysics from the University of Colorado in 1967. Following further work in molecular biology at Harvard University and at Cambridge, Altman joined the faculty of Yale University in 1971. Altman's research has concerned nucleic acid chemistry and the genetics of tRNA expression. In 1989 he won the Nobel Prize in chemistry. In addition to his teaching and research, Altman served as chairman of the Yale University Department of Biology from 1983-1985 and as dean of Yale College from 1985-1989.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, publications files, laboratory notebooks, edited manuscripts, and research data, which document Sidney Altman's research in nucleic acid chemistry.
Biochemistry; Molecular biology; Molecular genetics; Nucleic acids; Transfer RNA; Altman, Sidney; Yale University -- Faculty
- Original Accession
  Conditions Governing Access
  The material is unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu requesting specific box numbers in order to initiate the review process, which may take several weeks.
  - Publications files, sorted (Box 1–9)
  - Publications files, unsorted (Box 10)
  - General files [includes grant proposals, course of study and other Yale administrative materials, graduate student files, general correspondence] (Box 11–15)
  - Lab notebooks of Sidney Altman and graduate students [Harvard in black binders, Cambridge in green binders, Yale in blue binders] (Box 16–19, Box 19A)
  - Unsorted publications [from England] (Box 20)
  - Unsorted publications (Box 21–22)
  - Cal Tech material, virus studies, correspondence (Box 23)
  - Data [x-rays] (Box 24–51)
  - Illustrations for publications (Box 52–53)
- Additional Material, 1989-2010; Accession 2012-M-045
  Scope and Contents
  The 2012-M-045 addition to the Sidney Altman papers consists of edited manuscripts, research data, and correspondence arranged into three sections: Collaborative Research, Patents, and Topical Files. The Collaborative Research section is arranged by the last name of the collaborator with Dr. Altman; the Patents section is arranged by general files and then alphabetically by country; the Topical Files section is arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Collaborative Research
    - Eder, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
    - Eder, 1996-1997 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Gopalan, 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - Gopalan, 1998-2006 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
    - Guerrier-Takada, 1992-1995 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    - Jarrous, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Jarrous, 1997-1999 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
    - Jarrous, 1997-1999 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
    - Jiang, 2000 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Jiang, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Kirsebom, 1994-1998 (Box 7, Folder 3-5)
    - Ko, 2005-2008 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
    - Kovringina and Wesolowski, 2002 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Kovringina and Wesolowski, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
    - Krummel, 1999 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Li, 1995-2003 (Box 10, Folder 2-4)
    - Li, 2003 (Box 11, Folder 1-4)
    - Li, 2004-2005 (Box 12, Folder 1-5)
    - Liu, 1994-1996 (Box 13, Folder 1-5)
    - Liu, 1997 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Lunberg, 1994-1995 (Box 14, Folder 2-5)
    - Lunberg, Undated (Box 15, Folder 1-3)
      Contains lab notebooks on Crohn's disease research.
    - Lundblad, 2007-2008 (Box 15, Folder 4-5)
    - Plehn-Dujowich, 1998 (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
    - Salvati, 1997 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Seif, 2008 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Stolc, 1997-1998 (Box 17, Folder 2-4)
    - Vioque, 1999 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Westhof, 1993-1994 (Box 18, Folder 2-5)
    - Westhof, 1993-1996 (Box 19–21)
    - Yang, 2007 (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Yuan, 1993-1994 (Box 22, Folder 2-4)
    - Zhang, 2004 (Box 22, Folder 5-6)
  - Patents
    - General
      - Application materials and correspondence, 1989-1996 (Box 23, Folder 1-4)
      - Application materials and correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 24, Folder 1)
      - Notifications and correspondence, 2002 (Box 24, Folder 2-3)
    - Australia, 1997 (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - Canada, 1997 (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Europe [EU], 1996-1997 (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Europe [EU], 1996-1997 (Box 25, Folder 1-3)
    - Europe [EU], 1997 (Box 26, Folder 1-2)
    - Japan, 1999-2004 (Box 26, Folder 3-5)
    - United States, 1997-1998 (Box 27, Folder 1-2)
  - Topical Files
    - Chloroplast RNase P, 2000 (Box 27, Folder 3-4)
    - Data sets, 1995-1996 (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Data sets, 1995-1996 (Box 28, Folder 1-2)
    - E.Coli, 2000-2001 (Box 28, Folder 3-5)
    - Harcourt Brace Press, 1998 (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Innovir Laboratories, 1994-1995 (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - JB 91-02, 2002 (Box 29, Folder 3-5)
    - Lab notebooks, 1991-1992, undated (Box 30, Folder 1-4)
    - Masters of DNA, 2005 (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Microarrays, 2001 (Box 31, Folder 2-4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1995-2010 (Box 31, Folder 5-6)
      Includes manuscripts, research data and correspondence.
    - Pathogenesis Corporation, 1994-1995 (Box 32, Folder 1-5)
      Includes IPO documents.
    - Phenotypic conversions, 1997 (Box 33, Folder 1-3)
    - Publications correspondence, 1993 (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Ribozyme Pharmaceuticals, 1993-1994 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      Includes press releases and correspondence
    - RNA enzyme overview, 1997 (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - RNA World II, 1997-1998 (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - RNase P sub-units, 2005 (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - RNase P Structure and Contrast with Ribozymes, 2002 (Box 34, Folder 5-7)
    - Salmonella regulatory plasmids, 2002 (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - Sequence analysis, 2002 (Box 35, Folder 1-2)
    - Stress peptides, 2002-2009 (Box 35, Folder 3-5)
  - Computer files (Box 36)
    Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
- Additional Material, 1977-2011; Accession 2013-M-048
  This accession is closed to researchers until January 3, 2033, or the death of William H. McClain, Halvorson Professor, University of Wisconsin-Madison, whichever occurs first.
  This accession consists of published materials, correspondence, and related documents generated by William H. McClain, Halvorson Professor, University of Wisconsin-Madison, in his effort to credit Sidney Altman with the discovery of the enzymatic activity of bacterial ribonuclease P (RNase P) that resulted in his receipt of the 1989 Nobel Prize in Chemistry.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Materials in this accession were compiled by Sidney Altman.
  - Correspondence, 2009 June-2010 February (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Notes and research materials, 1977-2009 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Trials, Travails, and Triumphs: An Account of of RNA Catalysis in RNase P"
    - Drafts and notes, 2009-2011 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Final version, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 5)